Larry Bogart Papers 2012.0088
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Larry Bogart Papers
1958-2001
2012.0088
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
53.3 Linear feet
Papers of Larry Bogart, anti-nuclear power activist, are comprised of correspondence, administrative records, press releases, newsclippings, fliers, legal documents, scientific reports, government reports, newsletters, periodicals, typescripts, interviews, maps, books, audio recordings and photographs. The bulk of the collection dates from 1966 to 1986. The collection chronicles the extent of information available on nuclear energy as it was being published and circulated in local newspapers, government reports, books by American and European publishers, popular periodicals, the alternative press, and by individuals.
Bogart, Larry
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was acquired by donation in July 2012.
Arrangement and Description
The collection has been minimally processed and retains the loose chronological arrangement in which it was received. Subjects, organizations, and geographical locations mentioned in collection documents are highlighted in the finding aid for reference purposes.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Scope and Content
The Larry Bogart Papers are comprised of correspondence, administrative records, press releases, newsclippings, fliers, legal documents, scientific reports, government reports, newsletters, periodicals, typescripts, interviews, maps, books, audio recordings and photographs. The bulk of the collection dates from 1966 to 1986 and documents chronologically the activities of Larry Bogart and the organizations that he founded. The collection chronicles the extent of information available on nuclear energy as it was being published and circulated in local newspapers, government reports, books by American and European publishers, popular periodicals, the alternative press, and by individuals.
Biography/History
Larry [Herman] Bogart was among the earliest and most influential critics of using the atom to generate electricity, warning as early as 1963 that nuclear power plants were too complex, too expensive and too inherently unsafe to sustain anywhere in the world. Born in Brooklyn, New York in 1914, Bogart attended Phillips Exeter Academy and spent two years at Harvard University. After serving under General George Patton in World War II, he became a public relations executive at Allied Chemical Corporation in the early 1950s. At Allied Chemical, Larry Bogart wrote many of the company's news releases and promotional materials, including those relating to the benefits of nuclear power.
After intensive research, study of government documents, and interviews with scientists active in the field, he came to understand the harmful effects of ionizing radiation. In the early 1960s, when he discovered aspects of nuclear power that deeply concerned him, Bogart founded the Conservation Center and eventually the Anti-Pollution League. In 1966, he founded the Citizens Energy Council, the first national citizen organization opposed to the proliferation of nuclear power.
Bogart set out to organize study groups throughout the northeast to raise opposition to nuclear power plants proposed for Stamford, Connecticut; Tivoli, New York; Lake Champlain and Vernon, Vermont; Wiscasset and Sears Island, Maine; Newburyport, Ipswich and Rowley in Massachusetts; and North Kingston and Charlestown, Rhode Island. He advised groups that fought the construction of nuclear plants in New Jersey, New York, and Pennsylvania. He worked closely and tirelessly with citizens at the grassroots level throughout the United States, including California, Oregon, Michigan, Kansas, Ohio, Oklahoma, Tennessee, North and South Carolina, Virginia, and Maryland.
Larry Bogart worked for many years out of an office in Washington D.C. in order to regularly inform legislators about the harmful effects of nuclear energy on public citizens, and to curb further federal subsidization of nuclear technology. In the 1970s he worked at the state level, editing a number of newsletters and giving hundreds of talks and workshops. As National Coordinator of the Citizens Energy Council, he offered to "debate the nuclear power question with any scientists or executives before any public group".
According to the many citizens, public policy researchers and scientists that worked with him, Larry Bogart was instrumental in galvanizing public opinion, working at times with individuals and regional coalitions, against the hazards and human costs of nuclear power. He is often credited with founding the American anti-nuclear movement.
Larry Bogart died on August 19, 1991 when he was struck by a vehicle outside his home in East Orange, New Jersey.
Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence; Ephemera; Fliers [printed matter]; Manuscripts; Maps.; Photographs; Postcards.; Posters.; Publications.; Realia.
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1958-2001
  - Correspondence, photographs, fliers, posters, clippings, notes, publications, manuscripts, transcripts, undated, 1962-1964, 1966-1967; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include:
    New York World's fair, 1964/1965: Larry Bogart's correspondence with chemical/technical companies, including Union Carbide, Mobil, Xerox, etc. requesting sponsorship for planned "International Lounge" for foreign students at fair, working alongside The Greater New York Council for Foreign Students, Inc. (fliers for organization included); basic proposal for International Lounge also included; planning images (photographs) for fair from World's Fair Committee; correspondence forming advisory committee for "Chemistry at the Fair" (1962), associated with the Council for Education in the Sciences; planning Hall of Science Exhibit "Chemistry of Color" (1963), sponsored by General Aniline and Film Corp.
    Chemical company advocacy and public relations: Posters on Benzene, and products derived from coal and phenol; manuscript of publication titled "Allies of Defense," on the chemical industry; Larry Bogart composing booklet "Formula for Progress: Some Facts about Synthetic Organic Chemicals" (1963), for the Synthetic Organic Chemical Manufacturers Association.
    Anti-Pollution League: Opposing Burlington Nuclear Reactor (1967); Anti-Pollution League Bulletin (March, 1967); Publication "The Nuclear Failure at Indian Point" (undated); opposing Storm King Plant (1967; includes clippings); Publication from United States of America Federal Power Commission "Opinion No. 452" (1964).]
  - Clippings, publications, photographs, undated, 1971-1975, 1985-1986, 1989; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 2)
    Vermont Yankee Nuclear Plant (1972-1974), supported by U.S. Senator George D. Aiken (R-VT); Clippings from "Rocky Mountain News" on Radiation and Molybdenum Pollution; Manuscript on "Pumped Storage and Nuclear Power" by Jane Vanzandt Brower, PhD (10 April 1972); Bear Swamp Pumped Storage Project; Storm King Pumped Storage Plant; Indian Point (1985-1986); Shoreham, Long Island Plant; Publication "A Criticism of the Safety Evaluation of the Vermont Yankee Nuclear Power Station at Vernon, Vermont" by Irving Lyon; Montague Nuclear Power Plant (1974); U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission; 1975 Oil Crisis; Planned Seabrook Nuclear Power Plant (1971); New England Coalition on Nuclear Pollution news releases (1971); Northfield Mountain Accident (1972); Statement by Richard L. Ottinger of New York in the House of Representatives: "The Hudson: A River in Peril;" Chernobyl (1986); Nuclear Information and Resource Service National Day of Nuclear Protest (May 24, 1986); Publication "The Nuclear Monitor" (1989).]
  - Correspondence, publications, clippings, undated, 1963-1966, 1969, 1973, 1975-1976, 1986-1987, 1989-1990; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 3)
    Seabrook Nuclear Plant; Vermont Yankee Plant; Publication "The Elements," September-November 1975; Maine Yankee Plant; Montague Plant (1973); Pilgrim Plant, Plymouth (1986); Solar Hydrogen Energy; Global Warming: "The Warming of the World" by Carl Sagan (1987); "Hartmann Lines;" Mary H. Weik Newsletter, "Window on the World"; Ravenswood Reactor; Publications "Without Consent of the People: The Irresponsible Siting, Standards and Wastes of Atomic Power" and "The Story Nobody Prints: A Report on Health Conditions Around U.S. Atomic Plants" by Mary H. Weik; Indian Point (1965-1966); Conservation Center (Larry Bogart is director); Water Pollution (1965); Student Conservation Program Newsletter; Connecticut River Valley Pollution (1964); Conservation Center opposing Indian Point; Film Script Manuscript "Rebirth of a River" by Peter Jones; Anti-Pollution League (1965); Conservation Center's Clean Water Campaign and Friends of the Hudson; U.S. General Accounting Office Publication: "Energy: Bibliography of GAO Documents Jan. 1986-Dec. 1989;" Publication "Chernobyl: Possible Effect on U.S. Pop?" (1987); Publication "Defective Defense: How the Pentagon Buys Weapons that do not Work" by Louis Nemeth and Kukula Kapoor Glastris.]
  - Clippings, publications, notes, photographs, 1962, 1965-1969, 1971, 1982, 1985, 1989; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 4)
    Publications and articles: "Radiation Perils" newsletter (1989); Westingouse Electric Corporation 1967 Annual Report; Citizens Committee for the Hudson Valley publication "Facts you Should Know.... About the Proposed Hudson River Expressions and 117 Spur"; Booklet "Man is Destroying Himself: Can this be Prevented?"; "Business and Beauty: Remarks of Laurance S.; Rockefeller before 70th Annual Congress of American Industry, New York City, December 2, 1965"; Flier for "Radio Liberty," broadcaster of U.S. radio in USSR; "The Ecological Effects of Radiation" by George M. Woodwell (Scientific American, 1963); Report from Radiation Control Agency: "Radiation Environmental Survey: Hinsdale Area: Pilot Study;" Undated articles "Nuclear Threat Grows" and "Is the Nuclear Bubble about to Burst?"; U.S. Government Booklet "Atomic Energy and Civil Defense" (October 1967); Resources for the Future, Inc., Newsletter (1967); Anti-Pollution League Bulletin (June-July 1967); Manuscript "The Myth of 'Safe' Atomic Power Plants"; "New York's Water" Newsletter (April 1968); Citizens for Clean Air, Inc. Annual Report (May 1966-May 1967); "Questions of the NASA Accident of January 27, 1967 Raises with Regard to Possible Accidents at Nuclear Power Plants"; "Human Rights Action Guide 1978"; Friends of the Earth publication "Foe Log" (undated); "Boston Mobilizer" (June/July 1985).
    Organizations: Republicans and Independents Opposed to Rockefeller; Hudson River Valley Commission; New York State Conservation Council.
    Nuclear Power Plants: Indian Point, Vermont Yankee, Yankee Atomic Plant (Rowe, Mass.).
    Map of Atomic Power in the U.S. (1966).]
  - Correspondence, publication, flier, notes, maps, 1964-1966, 1981, 1983-1986, 1988; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 5)
    Articles and publications: flier "Pregnancy and Radiation"; publication "The Biological Effects of Ionizing Radiation: An Overview" by Mark H. Barnett, M.P.H.; Publication "Radiation and Women"; "Radiation: the Risks and the Benefits" by Henry N. Wagner, Jr.; "Statement: Friends of the Hudson, Mountmallen, N.Y."; Booklet "Do People Need a U.N. Vote?"; Publication "Critical Mass Bulletin" (1983); "Whitecrow" Newsletter; "On the Watch"; "New England Coalition on Nuclear Pollution, Inc. Public Education 1986 Bulletin No. 1"; "Three Mile Island Alert" Newsletter (October 1986); Publication "The Journal of Political Action Campaigns and Elections" (Spring 1984); "Whitewash: Painting over Management Problems at the Pilgrim Nuclear Plant 1986-1988" by MassPIRG; Article "'Three Mile Island Did It:' The Fatal Fallout from America's worst Nuclear Accident" by Harvey Wasserman; Report "Survey of Major National Grops Influencing Public Opinion Against Nuclear Power" Prepared by Terry R. Lash (1983).
    Organizations: Friends of the Hudson; New England Coalition on Nuclear Pollution; Jesse Jackson Presidential Campaign; National Rainbow Coalition, inc.
    Nuclear Plants: Seabrook, Storm King, Pilgrim Plant.
    Map: "Commercial Nuclear Power Stations Around the Word: Operable, Under Construction, or Ordered--Sept. 1, 1981".]
  - Clippings, fliers, clippings, manuscripts, notes, 1973, 1981-1985, 1988, 1990, 1997-1998; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 6)
    Articles and Publications: Report "More than Education: International Papers Expose Pro-Nuke Manipulation" (1982); Environmental Action Foundation Newsletter "The Power Line" (1981); Publication "Third World Resources: A Quarterly Review of Resources from and about the Third World;" flier on documentary film on Dioxin, "The Secret Agent"; Publication "Renewable Energy at the Crossroads"; "Nexus: the Journal for Computer Users in the Public Interest Community" (September/October 1983); Manuscript "Recipes with Miso, Sea Vegetables and Tofu: Traditional Japanese Foods Known to be Radio-Protective"; Newsletter "W.I.C. Crisis" (Women's International Coalition); flier "What if Chernobyl Happened in Connecticut?".
    Nuclear Plants: Seabrook, Vermont Yankee, Millstone, Indian Point.
    Organizations: Virginia Electric and Power Co.; Safe Energy Communication Council (SECC); Center for Renewable Resources; Radwatch (headed by Sara Shannon).
    Scripts for SECC Anti-Nuclear TV spots (1982-1985).
    Indian Point Weather Balloon Contamination Study (1997).]
  - Clippings, correspondence, 1968-1969, 1971-1973, 1975, 1989, 1991-1998, 2000; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 7)
    Articles and Publications: List of the "Fifty Worst Atomic Plants"; Publication "EMFR Monitor"; Article "The Controllers: Mind Control and Project MKULTRA" by Martin Cannon; Union of Concerned Scientists newsletter "Nucleus"; Article "Nuclear Hazards by Bernadette Geiger-Counter; "Synthesis/Regeneration 10: A Magazine of Green Social Thought"; Booklet "When Doctors Disagree", on the dangers of water fluoridation; Publication "National Fluoridation News" (1969); Book "Offshore Nuclear Generating Station" from General Electric (Vols. 2-3).
    Organizations: Sara Shannon Health Program; Radwatch; International Medcom (manufacturer of Radalert device); National Alliance Against Fluoridation.
  - Clippings, publications, 1969-1970, 1973-1974, 1986, 1988-1990; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 8)
    Articles and Publications: Flier "You Can't Get Rid of Radioactive Waste from Nuclear Plants" (1974); publication "Earthquake at Giza" by Sheldon Novick; article "Radioactive Malevolence" by L. Douglass DeNike; Manuscript "The Consequences of Major Accidents at Rowe, Mass. and Vernon, VT--An Application of Wash-740" by Larry Gay (June, 1973); Publication "The Radioactive Rag" (Fall, 1989); Publication "The Radioactive Waste Bulletin"; Citizens Clearinghouse for Hazardous Waste, inc. publication "Everyone's Backyard" (1988); Publication "Draft: Reused Siting Criteria Report for the New Jersey Low-Level Radioactive Waste Facility Siting Project"; Article "Tobacco Radioactivity and Cancer in Smokers".
    Organizations: U.S. Atomic Energy Commission; Hudson Valley Citizens Watch; Citizens Energy Council.
    Nuclear Plants: Savannah River Plant (South Carolina); Surry Nuclear Plant; Hanford; Davis-Besse Nuclear Plant (Ohio, 1970); Maine Yankee (1969); Vermont Yankee (1986); Three Mile Island.
    Other Topics: Radioactive Waste Disposal; Siting radioactive waste disposal area in Alabama (1970) and South Carolina; Depleted fisheries as a result of radioactive waste, particularly on the Hudson; possibility of sabotage and theft of reactors and radioactive fuel, and the illicit private construction of nuclear bombs, with the possibility of nuclear terrorism (clippings); Nuclear weapon storage; Accidents at "Nixon's Nuclear Plant," Surry Nuclear Plant (1974 radiation spill), and Hanford (1974 radiation leak); Pennsylvania Insurance Department insuring against nuclear damages; Yucca Mountain Storage; Food irradiation as a preservative.]
  - Correspondence, clippings, publications, fliers, 1964-1965, 1971, 1973, 1977-1978, 1990; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 9)
    Articles and Publications: Flier "The Nuclear Threat in Tennessee?"; Article "The Oppenheimer Case: A Study in the Abuse of Law" by Harold P. Green (September 1977); Publication "Earth's Enemy #1: Radioactive Pollution"; Publication "Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists (November 1974); Publication "A staff Report on Monthly Report of Cost and Quality of Fuels for Steam-Electric Plant"; Flier "Evacuation Following a Nuclear Accident"; Article "Radiation Doses and Effects in a Nuclear Power Economy: Myths Vs. Realities" by John W. Gofman; Thesis Manuscript: "Citizen Groups and Complex Technology: The Nuclear Power Issue, with Focus on Seabrook, New Hampshire" by Charles Purinton Shimer.
    Organizations: Citizens Energy Council (1965); Hudson River Conservation Society, inc. (1964); Friends of the Hudson; U.S. Department of Energy, Nuclear Waste Management; Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
    Nuclear Plants: Seabrook.
    Other Items: Poster on "Nuclear Power in the Hudson Valley"; Data graph on the "Effect of Conservation and Renewable Fuel on Purchased Energy Use".]
  - Publications, fliers, correspondence, clippings, photographs (negatives and prints), 1954, 1966, 1968, 1970-1976, 1978-1979, 1990; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 10)
    Articles and Publications: Flier "Nuclear Energy: Questions and Answers; Publication "Citizens' Energy Project Report Series No. 28: Nuclear Power: The Invisible Killer" by David Holzman; Publication "Counter-Point: The Newsletter of the Alliance to Close Indian Point; Pennsylvania Insurance Department publication "Citizen's Bill of Rights and Consumer's Guide to Nuclear Power (1973); Transcript "Statement by Ralph Nader before the Joint Committee on Atomic Energy Jan. 28, 1974, Washington, DC"; Publication "Nuclear Power Safety: An Engineering Overview" by Carl C. Hocever, Union of Concerned Scientist (1975); Article "The Case Against the Fast Breeder Reactor" by Amory B. Lovins; Publication "The Forgotten Citizen: Victim of Decision-Maker?" by Mary Hays Weik; Article "Environmental Contamination from Nuclear Reactors" by Malcolm L. Peterson; Article "The Monroe Doctrine: Past-Present-Future" By John Howland Snow (1954).
    Organizations: Friends of the Hudson; Citizens Committee for Protection of the Environment; Chernobyl-on-the-Hudson (1990); New England Coalition on Nuclear Pollution; Committee for Nuclear Responsibility.
    Nuclear Plants: Indian Point (1978); Vermont Yankee; Connecticut Yankee; Seabrook.
    Photographic prints and negatives of Indian Point Plant.
    Other Topics: Vermont Governor Thomas P. Salmon; Radioactive waste disposal; Nixon's Resignation; 1971 Fuel Shortage.]
  - Clippings, publications, maps, books, correspondence, ephemera, transcripts, fliers, 1966-1969, 1971, 1973, 1977, 1983, 1986-1989; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 11)
    Articles and Publications: James C. Cleveland (R-NH) press release "Cleveland Reports on Energy" (Sept. 28, 1973); Article "Vermont Yankee: Walking the Tightrope of Nuclear Safety: The Mighty White Elephant on the Banks of the Connecticut" by Edward B. Pickett; Book "An Essay on Morals" by Philip Wylie; Transcript of National Society for Clean Air Annual Conference, 1967 Des Voeux Memorial Lecture "Clean air and Future Energy" by Dr. E.F. Schumacher; Publication "Proposed Criteria Governing Thermal Discharge" (1968); Article "Naval Nuclear Accidents: The Secret History" by William M. Arkin and Joshua Handler (1989); Union of Concerned Scientists periodical "Nucleus" (1988); Natural Resources Defense Council Publication "Nuclear Winter's Silent Spring;" Sermons and "Apostle Report" publications from the "Church of Jesus Power" (1986-1988); Publication "Nuclear Power: The Hidden Costs;" Flier on irradiated food, titled "Is it Safe to Eat?"; "Counter-Point" newsletter; Folder: "1988: An End to Nuclear Power Souvenir Literature Packet."
    Organizations: United States Atomic Energy Commission; National Society for Clean Air; New York State Water Resources Commission; Union of Concerned Scientists; Natural Resources Defense Council; Church of Jesus Power.
    Nuclear Plants: Vermont Yankee, Newbold Island, Pilgrim, Indian Point, Shoreham.
    Other Items: Map of "40 Reactors Now Slated for Northeast--Mar. 1969;" clippings on health effects of radiation.
    Other Topics: Energy conservation; Vermont Gov. Thomas P. Salmon; Attempted Shutdown of Pilgrim and Vermont Yankee Reactors (1973); 1973 Energy Shortage; Vermont Gov. Deane C. Davis (1971); Water contamination on Connecticut River; Underground atomic weapons testing in Nevada; Death of 6,400 sheep in Skull Valley, Utah; Thermal discharge from nuclear reactors; NASA and Plutonium; Food irradiation.]
  - Clippings, publications, fliers, publications, correspondence, manuscripts, 1968-1971-1972, 1977-1979, 1981-1983, 1986-1991, 1996; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 12)
    Articles and Publications: Publication "Monitoring Maine Yankee: Report of the Citizens' Monitoring Network 1979-1988, Bath, Maine, August 1988" by Maria Holt and Elisabeth King; filer "The Most Imporant Thing in the World" (1978); "Nucleus" newsletter (1990); "Energy News Digest" periodical; GAO Report on Greenhouse Effect (1990); Publication "Radwaste Report" (1990); Greenpeace publication "The Failure of the 1990 Montreal Protocol;" Manuscript "Summary of Infant Mortality Changes in New Hampshire Following the Accidents at the Pilgrim Nuclear Reactor in the Summer of 1982" by E.J. Sternglass; Sternglass paper "Nuclear Air Pollution, Infant Mortality and Lung Disease" (1970); Publication "Scientist and Citizen" (May 1968); "Peaceletter" publication; Publication "People, Pride, and Progress: Central Hudson annual Report 1986."
    Organizations: Citizens' Monitoring Network; Sara Shannon Health Program; Citizens' Energy Council; United States Nuclear Regulatory Commission; Greenpeace; Black Hills Alliance; Friends of the Hudson.
    Nuclear Plants: Maine Yankee, Shoreham, Chernobyl, Seabrook, Indian Point.
    Other Items: Correspondence from Sara Shannon to Larry Bogart; Graphs illustrating correlation between nuclear power and weapons and the mortality rate; Larry Bogart's short autobiographical description of his anti-nuclear career (1969).
    Other Topics: Food Irradiation (1989); Yucca Mountain (1971); Nuclear Waste disposal in New York State; Nuclear pollution in Alaska; Nuclear test effects on SAT scores; Uranium mining in Black Hills.]
  - Correspondence, publications, books, maps, posters, manuscripts, 1957, 1967-1969, 1974-1982, 1984, 1988-1989, 1990; 1.3 Linear feet Foldered (Box 13)